Last we left our heroes. It’s a good reference that nobody got. It’s okay. Okay, we saw we're gonna hopefully finish Kuf Kaf Gimmel, yeah. Okay, so last we left, we saw the Gemara in source 63. The Gemara in source 63 that told us that Rav Pappa would
make sure to drink the beer outside, make sure to drink the beer outside of the store, Rav Hai would drink the beer outside of his home, and it seemed to pasken that we really only applies to something we call like the Rama was pretty lenient about it. Okay, so now we're just gonna pick up a few examples and this should wrap up Kuf Kaf Gimmel and then we'll start with Kuf Kaf Daled. Okay, first let's go to source 68. Source
68, okay, the Vilna Gaon here, so the Shulchan Aruch says that כל שכר של עובדי כוכבים ואחד שכר של תמרים וחטין ושל תבואה ושל דבש אסור משום חתנות. We did this a little bit last week. Of sugar or of honey is assur
mishum chasnuss and the Rama was pretty lenient. Here the Gra in Sif Katan Heh on the left side there in source 68, so the Vilna Gaon refers from the wording of the Shulchan Aruch that he paskens like Rav Hai, לשון רמב\"ם וגמרא שם כרב האי, which means that non-Jewish beer may only be drunk at home, which presumably present a problem. Hold on to the for the Kaf Hachaim for a second. If you go to source
70, which is the Darkei Teshuva paskens like Rav Pappa. דאיכא משמעות דברי השס דלאו דוקא אם הביא השכר לביתו אלא אפילו מוציאו חוץ לחנותו ושותה פתח חנותו שרי. So the Darkei Teshuva said no, no, even having outside the bar would be allowed. Okay fine, so that's sort of halacha le-maaseh. We're going to do a few examples to wrap it up. Example number one: if you go to source 71, can you have a beer? Again, there are people that do actually
enjoy beer. I do not. I've tried many times. I still don't understand it. But if you're the guy that likes beer, can you have a beer with a coworker at a restaurant? And this is assuming that we don't pasken like the Rama. Correct. Why why why? Because according to the Rama the only issue would be beiso. Oh, yeah, okay, yeah. Okay, so first, if you look in 71 in the Bach, right. To Joel's point, according to the Rama it's going to be allowed. The Shulchan Aruch and
the Gra would assur it, but according to the Rama it would allow it. So within the Shulchan Aruch and the Gra, the Bach paskens that even drinking alone in the home or establishment of a non-Jew is going to be assur. Says the Bach, שותה בבית ישראל דאילו בבית הגוי אפילו שותה ביחיד. Now, I don't know why this is happening, but if you were in this place by yourself even that would be a problem. It's not only a problem when there's somebody else there and we're gonna start shmoozing and talking together, even just
drinking alone is going to be an issue. But if you look in source 72 in the Piskei Teshuvos, in source 72, he quotes Rav Moshe. So what do those, however, we know that there are people that will have business meetings and they'll get a beer. How was that allowed? So says quoting Rav Moshe Feinstein, בכל מקום שעלה להתעורר איבה וקטטה מחמת מניעת שתייתו. Remember,
it's not really assur, the Rama already allows it. Within the Shulchan Aruch and the Gra they're more machmir, but when there is eivah and you worry that it's going to be bad, רשאי להקל ולשתות אצל השכר. If refusing is going to cause animosity between you and the goi, we're going to allow it. No shaya, you should not drink beer on your in your job. Yes, I don't drink it at all. I'm just making sure. You don't like any of the alcohol? Yeah, Rabbi and I have a special room in his job for... My question is: is there
a difference between going out to drink and going out and having a drink? Meaning if you're going out for the business meeting and you have a drink, is that different than going out to drink with... Yes, Rav Moshe would say yes. Meaning the baseline is that it's assur because you follow like the Gra and the Shulchan Aruch, meaning the Rama allows it but you shouldn't do it. If you're going to do it, you have to have a reason that's allowing you to do it. That would be eivah or something like that. Now if they say hey, can we go out for a drink? And you worry you have to, you have to evaluate that on your own, but yeah, I would think Rav Moshe would agree. Yeah, doctor. Just an
observation on the situation. Most business meetings, if you hold the drink and don't drink it, it usually happens. Correct. Correct. It's not maris ayin issues, right? Yeah, you could sit there, you could sit there and you could, you know, pour some out while no one's looking, right? Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Okay. Fine. There's a bunch of other examples here that they give in the notes that you can, you can look at. It's interesting this is, if you look at, if
you go back, yeah, if you look at the Kaf Hachayim. So there's an interesting shaylah we, when we talked about Starbucks, we talked about Starbucks from a kashrus standpoint. There is a shaylah of drinking at Starbucks because Starbucks is not a coffee shop. Starbucks is a treif restaurant that also offers coffee. So the shaylah is, when Starbucks became popular, this actually was more of the shaylah, before the whole stuff with the kashrus and all that.
There was a shaylah of is it a beis mishteh l'goyim, is it a beis mishteh l'goyim? How could, if it's stam a coffee place, okay, so you can go to a coffee place. But if it's offering all of these things, so that became, became a shaylah. So the again, the Rama would say it's not a problem. You can do it. Why? I can have coffee. So or could get other beverages. The Gra would seem to assur it. There if you look in the Kaf Hachayim. It's not a restaurant that also... Ah, okay, good, yeah, very good, very good, very good, very good.
Yeah. So it would seem that according to certain opinions, I could get a coffee at Starbucks, meaning some will say you can't get coffee at Starbucks. But let's assume you can get a coffee at Starbucks, you probably could get the coffee at Starbucks but you can't drink it there. Okay. So, so. You can't even go and work on your computer. That's what we're talking about! That's what we'd say assur. It's a beis mishteh l'goyim. It's a non-kosher restaurant. They don't sell, I mean, at least in the Shulchan Aruch, we're talking about shichra
over there. Ah, okay, okay. Very good. Okay. So, the shaylah is, but I just want to point out, I want to go, I'm not, I just want to go. As pointed out, the doctor's pointing out it's a different kind of place. So says the Kaf Hachayim. Lemaisa, the Kaf Hachayim disagree, there are those who disagree with the Gra and say it's fine, that when we're talking this whole thing is about alcoholic beverages. If coffee's going to be allowed, so the Kaf Hachayim says: מיהו מותר לשתות קפה של גוים בבית עובדי כוכבים דאינו משום בישולי גוים. We're not,
we're talking about that, we're talking about alcoholic beverages. We are not talking about coffee. Pri Chadash, Machneh Panim, the Beis Lechem Yehuda, and he wrote דלא כשו\"ת הפנים מאירות that assur'd it and it's brought in the Pischei Teshuva and he wrote there, Zivchei Tzedek שכן נהגו במדינות בגדאד יע\"א ששותים הקפה בבית הגוים that they would drink it there. So what emerges is the following. According to the Rama, only date beer is forbidden because that is assur to drink in a non-kosher
establishment. Fine. Shulchan Aruch and the Gra, like we saw earlier, alcoholic beverages are prohibited in a non-Jewish establishment. Coffee would be okay. Rav Moshe is going to allow some alcoholic beverages, you know, I'm sorry, even alcoholic beverages if it's because of eivah. Now, says the Chochmas Adam in source 74. That you're right about
coffee, אך בעונותינו הרבים בזמן הזה כמה קלקולים בזה בא מזה ובפרט לשתות קפה עם חלב שהוא אסור גמור שעל ידי זה חס וחלילה באים לידי נשק הידוע. על כן כאשר בו ריח תורה ירחק מזה מללכת לבתיהם לשתות איזה משקה שיהיה. You want to be a good Jew, take the coffee, drink it at home. Why you gotta sit with all the goyim? Why you know ah, ah, I'm I want to be one of, I'm an ohr la'goyim, tikkun olam. I'm going to influence everybody around me by my working on my laptop. All right, if you want to talk
about influences, probably better says, says the Chochmas Adam, to buy it but maybe drink it, you know, drink it somewhere else. This by the way, there were poskim, Rav Shechter himself is not such a fan of like, you know, drinking coffee in like non-kosher places. It's not maybe assur assur, but it's not, it's maybe not what he, you know. Happens to be there is a science behind the fact that if you work at places other than your work, you work better. There's like a science why
people work better on airplanes and in coffee stores and on like, you ever realize like on vacation you'll get more work done somehow? There's like a science behind it, but nonetheless there is a, you know, Rav Shechter is not a fan of like going out to all these places, so anyway. But if you're leading a group of people then you should go out with them? What do you mean leading a group of people? Rav Schechter would say don't go. Don't go. What do you have to go? You're going to sit around people who are going to be talking inappropriately, you're going to be seeing things, you're going to be looking at things, okay, it's better not to drink it there.
But what's the Chachmas Adam saying about it though? I'm saying I'm leading a group of students. What do you do? You're in charge of them and they want to go and they want to eat a sandwich, they go have a cup of coffee. Is it okay or not? It's okay. I'm saying that that's like when at Henne Sax at the Vaad Hachinuch we do a Q&A with the girls every month. So one of the questions a few like last time was is it better to wear loose fitting
pants or a tight skirt? I said why are those my only options? Meaning neither of those are going to be great options potentially. Meaning if you're mamash in the middle of nowhere, the only place is Starbucks. I go, I'm saying I work in Starbucks. But I'm saying Rav Schechter is accepts this chumra of the Chachmas Adam. So ask Rav Schechter, I have a group of students, he'll tell you: grab some coffees and sit outside or you know or bring it to a park. What's the Chachmas Adam talking about? That it might come to going through drinking
coffee. I mean I understand the milk issue, Cholow Yisroel, but then it's going to come to zenus. I feel like it's a the type of coffee shop he's describing. Could be, it could be. Yeah, yeah, like sitting by yourself on your laptop, it's not a... Anyway, I'm saying that's the, you know, look, I'll say one more. If you look in the Kuntres Hasmah, okay, in the Kuntres Hasmah there was something in the 1500s, 1600s, actually went into the 1700s, called the Vaad Arba Aratzos. The Vaad Arba Aratzos was a vaad of different communities in Poland and they had a lot of legal
authority to do certain things from the government. It was called the Vaad Arba Aratzos. The Levush was involved at one point. So he writes here that even though he says, אדם יקבע עצמו לשתות בבית משתה של גוי והקובע עצמו לשתות שם, you shouldn't do it. And one who does it, even though the Rema permits it, the Rema says you could do it. He permits drinking with non-Jews at a bar because that's the, we didn't asser that.
Nonetheless, it's בכלל הריקים והפוחזים ולא יקרא בשם רב חבר. That's pretty, pretty stark. That basically means like if you're doing this, you're not a rav. You're not even a chaver. Okay, forget smicha, chaver. V'lo yeshamnuhu bakehillah and you shouldn't really be involved in the, you know, in the community. So again, to your point. If you're nowhere to go, Rav Schechter would say accept this Chachmas Adam. You shouldn't, you shouldn't do it, it's better not to. This is true for a lot of things. It's better not to involve, but if it's not saying it's assur assur, it's a chumra of the Chachmas Adam. There are
times you have a meikil, you got a group of people, they want to grab a coffee, you know, people do work there and maybe it's become more of a workspace. But that is the chumra of the, again, Rav Schechter is not, he's not like I need to prepare a shiur so I'll go to Starbucks to work on it, like, you know. This would apply in Israel in a coffee shop that's owned by Jews and everybody there is Jewish? What? No. No, it's a Jewish place. The concept is good. Doesn't apply to... I mean, otherwise we can never go out to eat... Does
it matter if you're worried about non-Jews being there? No, no, no, no, no. Owned by non-Jews. Yeah. What about people going...? What if they're going to be Arab workers? No, no, no. No. There might be bishul like yayin, bishul, mevushal questions, but no, no, that wouldn't apply. That would be otherwise we never could go to restaurants here. What about people going on dates in a hotel lobby? They have a drink, would that be assur on this? So probably not. Meaning a hotel lobby, if you go to like, a hotel lobby has a bar... Okay, okay, fine. So if
you go to like, Yoko has like two and a half tables outside, okay? So if you, if let's say Yoko wasn't a kosher restaurant, eating outside is not what the Rema is, not what the Gemara is talking about. But a hotel lobby that has a little bar but has a massive lobby, I think would be considered different. That would be, that's a lobby that also happens to have a bar that's nearby, but it's not a bar. But like sitting in like the lounge area might be? I'm not sure. I'm not sure. That's a good shaila. I don't think so. I think it's not defined
as like as a restaurant. It's very, very open. Could be. Yeah. Okay, fine. This is the Chachmas Adam, it's important to know. But again, there's many meikils. Next time you see me working in Starbucks, don't, don't throw this Chachmas Adam at me. I'm working towards it. Okay. Yeah. Okay. So let's go to the next, the next issue, and that is not only restaurants and things like that, but what about we discussed already drinking at the non-Jewish bars
and coffee and places like that? Can you drink anything at a party that is hosted by a non-Jew? Okay? So says the Rambam in Source 76. Okay? Source 76, this... It could be a company party, it could be a, you know, a lot of shailos come like this when people go to, you know, simchos, I guess they're not called, but weddings of non-Jewish friends and coworkers, things like that. Can you? Alright, they happen to be that there's Moscato there. Oh, look at that.
Can you drink in a place like that? So says the Rambam in source 76. Keitzad, so the Rambam here is discussing that you really can't drink even mevushal wine. כיצד לא ישתה אדם במסיבה של עכו״ם you should not be drinking at a party of non-Jews. ואף על פי שהיין מבושל שאינו נאסר ושהוא שותה מכליו לבדו, right? Even if even if it's your kelim, right? Even if the kelim belong to you, you brought your own drink. You can't drink that. אם היה
רוב המסיבה ישראל מותר if the most of the party is majority are Jewish, then it's considered a Jewish party. ואין שותין שכר שלהן של התמרים משום עבודה זרה, you should obviously drink their own beer of from the tamrim. ואם הביא השכר לביתו מותר שעיקר הגזירה שמא יסעוד אצלו. The main main issue is that what, what, what don't we want you to do? We don't want you to have mixed dancing. We don't want you to start sitting and shmoozing and having like a
full-on, you know, conversation and things where that will lead to. Now, the shaila is when the Rambam says this halacha, where's the Rambam's source for such halacha? We know the Rambam's Mishneh Torah doesn't quote you Gemaras, but the Rambam gets it from somewhere. So first, the Gemara in Megilla, I'm sorry, yes, well, the Mirkavas Hamishneh in source 77 says, \"I know where this comes from.\" Where would this come from by the way? Anybody want to take a guess? Mesibas shel
Achashveirosh. Didn't go well for the Jews. אם היה רוב המסיבה ישראל, I think the Berachos daf nun-vav is סתם מסיבת נכרים לעבודה זרה, ואף אם רוב ישראל מברך. In Megilla, שנהנה מסעודתו של אותו רשע. Why was the fate sealed by the Jews on on Purim? Because they were neheneh from the seuda of Achashveirosh. The problem is that this halacha does not find its way to the Shulchan Aruch. Shulchan Aruch does not quote
this, the Remu doesn't quote it, it's not in the Shach and the Taz and the Piskei Teshuvos doesn't seem to quote it. It's quoted by Acharonim but it's not brought down. Most Rambams are going to be brought down the Shulchan Aruch. So now. Was it discussed in Megilla, Masechta Megilla? It is discussed. It is discussed, but it's not brought down in halacha. Right. But Achashveirosh was with pouring the wine. Hold on, take a step back. No one's denying that this didn't happen in the story of Purim. What I'm saying is
it's not quoted halacha l'maaseh in the Shulchan Aruch. Good? Good. Okay. By the way, the the Hebron Rosh Yeshiva says that the Gemara is actually davka שנהנה מסעודתו של אותו רשע, not that they drank מסעודתו של אותו רשע. They could be they had to go, eivah, all these different issues, but they were neheneh. They also I believe that, you know, Hashem give up on them. But it wasn't rov Yisrael, right?
No. Rov Yisrael at the party? I don't think so. I don't know that that would make a difference in the story of Achashveirosh. Whatever, we can go back and re-read. But Achashveirosh was giving, pouring the wine for them. Hold on one second. There is a major chilluk between slaves to a country who are forced to go to a party versus happens to be that my non-Jewish coworker's party eighty Jews signed up and versus sixty of the goyim. Weiter, says Rav Moshe Feinstein. Bidvar la'asos parlor, you want to have a parlor meeting
beveis nochrim. So happens to be someone's hosting something, but it's in the house of a goy. Afilu l'tzorech mitzvah, maybe it's something important, it's advocacy, it's whatever it may be. That's assur משום שעיקר איסור לעשות משתה בבית נכרים. Like the Rambam. אפילו לאכול שם דברים המותרים. Even if they had Liebers cookies. Doesn't matter. That that is a party of goyim, you cannot eat there. So now, granted it's not going to happen that much, but
Rav Moshe writes כיון שהוא דבר איסור משא״כ בדבר שלא שייך להתיר אפילו לצורך מצווה. It wouldn't matter. It wouldn't matter the reason that something is happening if it's hosted by goyim and you are there. You could go, you just can't eat and you can't drink. That's how the Rambam paskens. ולא דמי לנכרי עצמו עושה משתה לאיזו שמחה. So then Rav Moshe says the prohibition is when if the Jews are the ones organizing the party in a non-Jewish place, meaning we're going to do some,
you know, city... Chicago thing that Agudah wants to do something but we found a prominent Goy to host it. That, that's the problem. If the Goy is hosting something, so listen, come to my house for something, so says Rav Moshe וזימן איזה יהודי שלא יוכל להשתמט מותר רשאי לילך וגם לשתות משקה מותר משום איבה. If the Goy himself says listen I want to host a parlor meeting and I want you to come and you say listen I'm really sorry but the Rav Moshe says I can't come, that's not going to be good. Again, because we're in this very gray
area where we're allowed to be mekil on certain things, Rav Moshe says that would be okay. והשתיה נחשבת מילא עראי, it's very arai, you're not having how often this parlor meeting is not happening weekly. No one has a weekly parlor meeting. אבל הפרלור מיטינג הרי עושים בכוונה של היהודי בבית הנכרי שזה אין להתיר. So Rav Moshe says if the event's being organized and hosted by non-Jews and failing to attend is an eivah, that's okay. Really what we're talking about is that we're hosting something but it's in the Goy's house and then why we're not be able to participate and do not think this is such a major major issue.
Even more lenient is source seventy-nine and that is רב בן ציון אבא שאול. He asks דשאלות מסיבה שמשתתפים בה נכרים. Is a party that has non-Jews, המותר לשתות שם משקאות? Says רב בן ציון אבא שאול מסיבה שרובה נכרים אין לשתות שם משקה מבושם כגון עראק ובירה וכדומה. Now you can't drink you know what they have. So on the one hand he's going to be... Why would you want to drink arak?
It's Pesach. Is that the one that's allowed on Pesach? Yes. Look at that. I like it. It's not considered alcohol. Do you drink it during the year? No. Good for you. So he says, ואף בירה שבכלל זה. So רב בן ציון אבא שאול is on the one hand mekil or more mekil or more machmir? He's more lenient that he says you can go, even if you can go, I don't care, it doesn't have to be eivah. You can go, enjoy the party. But he says you really really can't drink at all. But again
he says, אם רוב בני המסיבה יהודים כגון חתונה של יהודים שיש גויים משתתפים בחתונה, it's a Jewish, there's אין איסור לשתות שם. Again he would agree that if a majority of the attendees are Jews it would be okay to participate. Okay. In the same like these are shailas, you know companies are having holiday parties. Companies, somebody had called me up, he's having, he was having a company like, you know, a work appreciation event. It's the same kind of thing.
It's the same kind of thing. So those events Rav Moshe will say if it's al menat I can't go, you go, and either you don't drink like or you know, but but definitely definitely not going because of the eivah would be a problem. Okay fine. Let's just see there's one, yeah okay, one more and then we'll finish סימן קכג which is a very very, it was a very very big Siman. In the שאלות ותשובות שבט הלוי he says the following. The shaila was asked,
could a ger eat at his non-Jewish father's birthday party? Okay? So he says you could go for three reasons. He says, mutar lalechet sham, you should go. He says, איסור זה לא כל כך מקובל בינינו במדינה זו, we have not seen that like everybody's so makpid about these things, number one. ועוד יש כאן עניין של איבה, sorry I can't participate because I am Jewish now, that's going to be very bad. וגם כיבוד אב, היסוד
של כיבוד אב שאף גויים מחוייבים במצווה זו באופן מסוים, they have them they have, so therefore he says you absolute you absolutely should go. Okay. Good. Next. Kuf Chaf Dalet. Okay. So סימן קכד is now who actually can asser the wine that we are talking about? Okay, what kind of Goy? Non-religious, things like that. Okay we'll see some very
very interesting opinions here. A lot of this stuff you might have heard thrown about around you know discussed in different context. But Chazal structured this issur, the gezeira of drinking wine, we wanted to make sure to forbid intermarriage so who exactly is involved in that prohibition? Who who can't touch my wine? So number one we're going to discuss that. And does what do they have to do? They have to move it, touch it, drink it, what how do they asser? So let's go to the Shulchan Aruch for a second. Okay. If you look in the Shulchan Aruch in
Sif Alef, קכד א. Says the Shulchan Aruch, tinok, so a child. Okay, a little baby. Tinok oved kochavim, here it doesn't mean like you have a toddler who's like, you know, doing wine libations and bowing down to an idol. He's a Goyish baby. Okay let's call him Christopher. There's no Christopher. שאינו מזכיר עבודת כוכבים ומשמשיה,
he doesn't know anything. This is based on the Gemara we saw a little bit earlier. Non-Jewish baby touches Jewish-owned wine. Nonetheless, אינו אוסר במגעו אלא בשתייה. So if a non-Jewish baby touches that Jewish-owned wine, says the Shulchan Aruch that it would not necessarily, you can't drink it, but it would not be assur for benefit, okay? Veiter, beiz. Ger Toshav. A Ger Toshav, דהיינו שקיבל עליו שבע מצוות
בני נח, וכן גר שמל ולא טבל. Right? And a person who is almost Jewish. Oser bishtiyah. Right? Again, not really so common today. Now, if you look in the source, the first source in the booklet, the Tur. The Tur quotes a Rashba. Okay, it's a very, very important Rashba that we will come back to a few different times. Says the Tur: כתב הרשב״א כבר בארנו שגר תושב שקיבל עליו שבע מצוות יינו מותר בהנאה.
That a Ger Toshav who accepts שבע מצוות בני נח does not forbid the wine from benefit. Why? Now you can't drink it, you can't drink it, but you can benefit from it, okay? What did we say that in general about stam yeinam today? What? What? Yeah. Now, a Ger Toshav, why, why do we say that a Ger Toshav that touches your wine we're okay with it, we're okay with you benefiting still from it, why? Not yayin nesech. Why not? Because he accepts
שבע מצוות בני נח. I'm not worried he's going to do avodah zarah. Ah! So, in come, now by the way, we really should take like this whole, this one line in the Rashba could be an entire series on how we understand Islam. But says the Rashba: לפיכך יש מהגאונים שהתירו יינם של ישמעאלים. So the same would be true if a Muslim had touched your wine. Hold on a second! Bano, שהדבר ידוע שאינם עובדי עבודה זרה. Now, vechein katav
haRambam. Now this is not such a shocking thing to us because we believe that Muslims are not the, we do not define Islam as avodah zarah, right? Islam believes in one God, we believe in one God. Islam believes, right, in a being, we believe in a being. They don't believe in avodah zarah. Christianity is avodah zarah, right? Islam is not. We know this is true from halacha l'maaseh. You can enter a mosque, you can't enter a church, right? This is true the Rambam has a letter in Iggeres Teiman where
a person asked him. The Rambam has a few different letters. So in one of the letters, they asked him about they were the Jews in Yemen and they had all these issues. But he says if someone were to say to you convert to Islam or die, you convert. Why? All they want you to do is say I believe in their God. Okay, we do believe in a God. Now if they say convert to Christianity, then you have to die. There's a whole debate among historians if the Rambam at the end of his life converted to Islam to like escape
something. It's a very much debated, which is not in the, more of the historians. Anyway, that's if you look in the five, Islam has five tenets of faith. What, they have one called tzedaka, which ironically sounds a lot like tzedakah. Okay? The, there's two more that were added on later, that's like jihad is like six and then there's more, the original is not. Anyway, enough about Islam. If you look in the Rambam
in Hilchos Melachim, the Rambam says that והיה ה' למלך על כל הארץ. In the end of time, the whole goal will be that everybody recognizes Hakadosh Baruch Hu as king. So if you look at the two major religions of the world, Islam and Christianity, it covers I don't know how many billions of people that fall under one of those two religions. So Islam gets the God part right and the text part wrong, okay, New Testament, Old Testament, sorry, I'm sorry, they get the God part right but they get the Quran wrong.
Christianity gets the God part wrong and the text part right. So we're like two-thirds of the way there. והיה ה' למלך על כל הארץ, like eventually they'll realize that they're off. I just want to point out the mechanism is a bit different because a Ger Toshav has to accept these things, whereas Ishmael they just. Correct, correct, that's what the Rambam writes. Right, right, right. All you got to do is you got to say it, you don't have to do anything. Alu vehatzliachu. Right. Thank you. That's, it's recorded in perpetuity,
Eddie. It's going to be on, I'm going to run that on a loop in the parm-shop by the way. Okay. Next. So says the, in source number two, ספר בן ישראל והנכרי. That although the Rema earlier paskens that benefiting from wine from all non-Jews is okay, as Jules. Jules just pointed out since most non-Jews today don't really do anything, that's bedieved. והיינו אפילו לשיטתו דיינו של נכרי בזמן הזה אסור בהנאה. Divrei haRema is afilu b'sha'ar nachri. He is meikel. והני מילי יש שלא במקום הפסד. The Rema's meikel,
but he was meikel in a bedieved. דשאר גויים אסור בנחש שעובד עבודה זרה יהא מותר. What about these non-Jews that they don't worship avoda zara? You're right! So nonetheless, benefiting from wine touched by a Muslim would be bedieved. Meaning a goy, Christian who's not a real Christian, he doesn't really do libations. Alright, bedieved we can be meikel. But an Arab, a Muslim who touches your wine, why would it be assur at all? Even l'chatchila it should be mutar.
Says the Rav Ovadia in source number three, what happens if you're unsure if a specific non-Jew touched your wine? You had a big house party and there were a bunch of workers that came through and you don't know if one of them touched your wine. So he says, ספק סתם יינם או ספק מגע בין ביין שלנו של ישמעאל מותר אפילו בשתייה. If you think it was an Arab, a Muslim, sorry, you're good. You can drink it, cause the concern for chasnus is only d'rabbanan. Safek
d'rabbanan l'kulah. אבל ספק מגע הנוצרים ביין שלנו יש להחמיר. If your worker was a Christian and they maybe touched your wine, then safek d'oraisa l'chumra. Why? Cause they're goyim. If, sorry, even im d'oraisa, but even though it's only d'rabbanan, that's חומרה שלא נעשה בו חכמים. Meaning, I'm not worried that the goy Christian goy who came into my house took my wine, brought it home, did all the libations that they needed, brought it back to the bottle and took it home and brought it back to my
house. However, and even though that's only an issur d'rabbanan, nonetheless, if it's an issur d'rabbanan for a Muslim, we're going to be meikel. Why? Because that's mamash nothing. It's only a d'rabbanan of chasnus, and this is a Muslim, so there's no issue. If it's a d'rabbanan for the the Christian, we should be a little bit more machmir because of yayin nesech. We could be meikel because safek d'rabbanan l'kulah, but we're going to be machmir because of of the chumra of yayin nesech. So again,
bedieved we would be meikel, but lema'aseh we are pretty machmir about these things. For when it comes to, you know, your your non-Jewish Christian house, you know, I don't know, cleaner touched, moved your bottle of wine, potentially going to be an issue if it was open, if a lot of all these different kind of things. Okay. Now, what about, that's all, again, this is a very, very short summary because we're not getting into it about how we, why we define Christianity as avoda zara because they believe in, they believe in multiple gods. That is literally the definition of avoda
zara, the Son, the God, the Holy Ghost, there are three different gods. We believe in one God. What? What about Unitarians? Depends on which group of Christians. Okay, fine, we'll get into that a different time. We do not believe that Islam is considered avoda zara and therefore we would allow to be meikel on these shaylos. Now, what happens if somebody who is non-religious touches your wine? So, look at the Gemara in Chulin. Says the Gemara in Chulin. The pasuk says, m'chem v'lo m'kulchem when it
talks about korbanos. There are three halachos regarding your korbanos that are accepted in the Beis HaMikdash. Number one, l'hotzi es hamumer. A mumer is one who intentionally transgresses a law in the Torah out of like pure ideology. Not like they just forgot or they whatever. Like, I do not believe in netilas yadayim. That is made up, the rabbis made it up, we're not going to do it. That's a mumer, and a mumer you cannot accept a korban from.
Fine. Number one. Number two, a מכם בכם חלקתי ולא באומות. We only allow a Jew to, non-Jews could bring korbanos, but a neder korban is only from a Jew. And finally, the Gemara says: מן הבהמה להביא בני אדם שדומה לבהמה. Mikan amru: מקבלים קרבנות מפושעי ישראל. A Jew who sins because he sinned, we accept his korban sheyechazru b'teshuva. We hope that he does teshuva. Chutz, says the Gemara. Meaning we believe
very much, we're coming up to Yamim Noraim soon, we believe very much in the power of teshuva, so if somebody does something wrong of course we accept, poshei Yisrael's not like you can bring a korban chatas. We're talking here a poshei Yisrael, like mamash a real sinner. Do we want this guy, here comes sinner bringing his korban up the Beis HaMikdash, Har HaBayis, get out of here. No, we accept his korban because maybe he's going to do teshuva, he's going to be inspired. Says the Gemara, that's all fine and dandy except for a mumer, u'menaseich es hayayin,
one who does yayin nesech, right, who offers wine as avoda zara, and m'chalel Shabbosos b'farhesya. The reason is that a person who's m'chalel Shabbos b'farhesya. is because it's actually in the Rashba in the next source, a person who is mechalel shabbos b'farhesya is basically a oved avodah zarah. That shabbos is about emuna, right, shabbos is is reaffirming our faith, that's why the melachos of shabbos are things that we can't create. Right,
every melacha of shabbos is constructive, if it is destructive it's only issur d'rabonon. If it's destructive al menas to get constructive, it's that maybe, like סותר על מנת לבנות. But melachos on shabbos are constructive things, we couldn't build the mishkan on shabbos, so because we don't create, God is the only creator, we take a break to realize that Hakadosh Baruch Hu is the only creator. If I'm mechalel shabbos, I don't believe in Hakadosh Baruch Hu. I don't believe in Hakadosh Baruch Hu. So the Rashba says that a meshummad l'chalel shabbasos, that is like that's a avodah zarah.
And you have to do it, he says in the in the end, the last two lines, מוחזק בו שלשה פעמים, that you did it at least you know at least three times. Okay, it's not like a guy one time. But if a person is established as a real real mechalel shabbos. When I when I was in YU I went to I went to California, Palm Beach, West Palm- Palm Beach? Palm Springs. The Palm Springs for for Shavuos. I went- me and Rav Shechter's son Yumi from
who was you know we were both single, it was it was one of the wildest experiences of my life. And there a guy they my friend who was the son-in-law of the person who lived there, he was like the rabbi of the shul for a little bit. It was like 12 people in the shul, it was great. And a guy drove on- to the meal, okay, and he says to me, you think you think what I did was assur? That's what he asked me at the table. So of course being my young rabbinic self, said absolutely and I smacked him across the face.
I said whatever you gotta do. He says he looks he's like if I walk with these legs that's a melacha, turning my car on is not a melacha. That was a great psak and I've since accepted that as pretty much my baseline. So the Shulchan Aruch here before you get to- what what? It is assur. He said al hadvarah, I'm fine. What I said was fine. Okay, go to the Shulchan Aruch cheis, says the Shulchan Aruch, one more piece, he adds that mashoch b'orlaso, a person who who like extends his orla
to conceal his bris, אינו עושה יין נסך, that one who pulls his bris does not forbid the wine, ומומר אף על פי שמול עושה יין נסך במגעו. That that a person who is a mumar like we just said, that person is going to be a- is going to be a problem, he has the status of a non-Jew and it's assur b'mago, ונאמן לומר ששב בתשובה. And if he- he's allowed to say that no I I did teshuva. Okay.
Now, there is in the back, we're not going to look at it now, but there is- oh not here- there is a Shach in the Nekudos HaKesef. Yeah, I'm not quoting him but okay, so fine. If you look in source six for a second, okay look in source six for a second. The Shach paskins that if a mechalel shabbos, a real mechalel shabbos
b'farhesya. Now, you before you jump up and down and yell and scream, you know a lot of mechalelei shabbasos, I also do. The guy that doesn't know anything, the guy who's my non- my non-religious Jewish co-worker who wishes me a shana tova, is that considered- is that what we're talking about? We're going to get there. We're going to get there. But right now we're talking about a guy who is mamash mechalel shabbos for all for all intents and purposes, says the Shach, if he publicly violates shabbos and he touches your wine, that wine is assur, that wine
is assur. In source number six, the Shulchan Aruch paskins the following: ישראל מומר לעבודת אלילים או לחלל שבת בפרהסיא, it is a fascinating thing that we connect these two, or a person is mechalel shabbos, אפילו אינו מחלל אלא באיסור דרבנן, the guy says oh I'm for sure not going to cook on shabbos, but like I you know I don't do issurei d'rabonon. I mean I only don't do issurei d'raisa, issurei d'rabonon I have no problem with. הרי הוא כעובד אלילים,
that is like a person who is mamash a non-Jew. ואם אינו מחלל אלא בצנעה אפילו מחלל איסור דאורייתא, but if he does it only b'tzina and not b'farhesya, only in private and not in public, even if it's a d'raisa, הרי הוא ישראל ומבטל רשות. Why is that? Why b'tzina? Because b'tzina means that he still understands that he does something wrong. Okay. So what it seems that is that a person who publicly violates shabbos and he touches your wine, that wine is assur. So the question is why? Why-
why would that be the case? So look in the Teshuvos V'Hanhagos, okay, and what would we say today when we have a lot of people What would we say today when we have a lot of people that are mechallelei shabbosos? What would we say? Invite people for Shabbos? Well, we're not up to that yet. Says Rav Sternbuch, amnam, נראה שמחללי שבתות בפרהסיא בזמנינו. So Rav Sternbuch actually goes one more step, he says it's actually worse, chomer me-akum stam, דקבעו חז\"ל שמחללי שבת דינם כעובד עבודה זרה.
ואפילו דעכו\"ם שבינינו אינם עובדי עבודה זרה, מכל מקום לעניין מחללי שבת בפרהסיא קבעו חז\"ל שדינם כעובד עבודה זרה ממש. He says no. Chazal even today, there's no concern for intermarriage, a person who's mechallel shabbos befarhesya is going to be a problem if he touches your wine. Your problem if he touches your wine. Okay. So where does that leave us today? So we'll start this very very very important, there's two different shuvos, one here the Binyan Tzion and one a little bit later, but there
is a very very important shuva here the Binyan Tzion. And the question is like this: when we say people that are mechallel shabbos, what does that mean? Does that mean that I grew up, I know the halachos, and I outright say I don't believe this? That's a mechallel shabbos befarhesya. In our community, if you saw a guy who sat next to you in shul, 6:25 minyan every day, and on Shabbos he's driving down 2E, that's mechallel shabbos befarhesya. There's no, sorry David. Some people that are driving down 2E on Shabbos,
right? That, okay, but what about I have two aunts that are going to drive on Shabbos or going to say they come to your house and touch your wine and it's assur. So the Binyan Tzion was dealt with this shaila 150 60 years ago because people wanted to come to shul, they wanted to be involved in shul, but they were driving to shul. So what do you do? So the Binyan Tzion explains, we're going to run out of time. I'll come back to this inside next
week. But basically the Binyan Tzion is going to explain and then we'll discuss something there's two different things: there's Tinok Shenishba. And that is a guy who mamash doesn't know anything. He barely knows that he's Jewish. Versus a person who might have grown up in a religious world, but didn't keep it going, didn't accept it, all these different kind of things. The Binyan Tzion is very meikel those kind of things. First of all if the guy says I want to come to shul, what, we're going to say no? We'd rather you come and we're going to figure this out. Rabbi Reis has a beautiful beautiful article on this topic that if I can find it and scan it
out, I'll send it out after next week so you don't know.